A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor Edmund Randolph, 1786-1788
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Executive Papers, 1786-1788
Library of Virginia
40084
3.88 cubic feet
Governor's Office
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reel 4922-4928.
Miscellaneous Reel 4922 - 1786 Dec.-1787 Mar. 10
Miscellaneous Reel 4923 - 1787 Mar. 12-May 19
Miscellaneous Reel 4924 - 1787 May 21-Sept. 29
Miscellaneous Reel 4925 - 1787 Oct.-Dec.
Miscellaneous Reel 4926 - 1788 Jan.-May
Miscellaneous Reel 4927 - 1788 June-Oct.
Miscellaneous Reel 4928 - 1788 Nov.
Biographical Information
Edmund Jenings Randolph was born is Williamsburg, Virginia, on 10 August 1753. Randolph was the son of John & Ariana Jenings Randolph and nephew of Peyton Randolph, a member of the Continental Congress from 1774 to 1775. Edmund graduated from the College of William & Mary and proceeded to study law in Williamsburg. At the outbreak of the Revolutionary War, Randolph served as aide-de-camp to George Washington in the Continental Army. The following year, he married Elizabeth Nicholas and served as both the youngest delegate to Virginia's first Constitutional Convention & Mayor of Williamsburg. Randolph was elected the first Attorney General of Virginia and served until 1782. In addition, Randolph acted as a delegate to the Continental Congress for the years 1779, 1781, & 1782. He was elected by the General Assembly to two one-year terms as Governor from 30 November 1786 until 12 November 1788. During his first term as Governor, Randolph represented Virginia as a member of the U.S. Constitutional Convention in 1787. During the Convention, Randolph proposed his Virginia Plan for the Constitution with a strong central government and representation based on population. He opposed the final version of the Constitution, but later advocated its ratification with the proposed amendments. He was appointed the first Attorney General of the United States under President Washington serving from 1789 until 1794. Randolph then became Secretary of State, but was forced to resign on 19 August 1795. Following his political career, Randolph served as senior counsel to Aaron Burr during his trial for treason in 1807. Randolph died in Clarke County, Virginia, on 12 September 1813, and is buried in Old Chapel Cemetery, Millwood, Va.
Scope and Content Information
Governor Randolph's Executive papers are organized chronologically with undated items arranged at the end of each year. These papers primarily consist of incoming correspondence during Randolph's two one-year terms as governor between 30 November 1786 until 12 November 1788. These records include correspondence written to Beverley Randolph who acted as Lieutenant Governor while Edmund served as a member of the U.S. Constitutional Convention in Philadelphia in 1787. The correspondence in this collection relates to a variety of topics including appointments for state positions; the Point of Fork Arsenal; Indian attacks in the western country & peace treaties; Shay's Rebellion in Massachusetts; arms & ammunition; the Constitutional Convention in Philadelphia; the State Boats Patriot & Liberty; Revolutionary claims against Virginia and the United States; the Public Jail & prisoners; militia; the U.S. Board of Treasury; searchers; public finances; the state of Franklin; the independence of Vermont; tobacco; elections; the Northwestern territory; the District of Kentucky; and others. In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions from Congress and the Virginia Senate & House of Delegates; orders of the Council of State; accounts; oaths; pardons; lists or calendars of criminals; depositions; proclamations; petitions; reports; appointments; bonds; circulars; proceedings; applications; agreements; extracts of journals & minutes; registers of ships; and other sundry items.
Noteworthy correspondence originates from the United States government, Virginia State government, and miscellaneous sources. Prominent correspondents from the United States government include Thomas Jefferson, Minister of France; Charles Thomson, Secretary of Congress; John Jay, Secretary of Foreign Affairs; Henry Knox, Secretary of War; Joseph Martin, Agent of Indian Affairs; Samuel Osgood, Walter Livingston, & Arthur Lee, U.S. Board of Treasury; and the Virginia Delegates to Congress including Edward Carrington, William Grayson, James Madison, Jr., Henry Lee, William Heth, John Brown, Cyrus Griffin, & Richard Henry Lee.
Thomas Jefferson, as Minister of France, writes to Governor Randolph on 7 February 1787 regarding the inauguration ceremony of the bust of the Marquis de Lafayette. Jefferson also writes about shipments of arms from Bordeaux and payments to Houdon for the statue of General Washington and a second bust of Lafayette (1787 August 3). Lastly, Governor Randolph forwards to Beverley Randolph on 27 May 1787, a dispatch of W. Short enclosing the proceedings of the City of Paris on the reception of Lafayette's bust presented by the state of Virginia. This letter also encloses another letter from John Bondfield to Gen. George Washington concerning a shipment of arms to Dumfries.
Charles Thomson, Secretary of Congress, corresponds often with Randolph. He transmits Congressional journals, resolutions and acts of Congress, monthly States of Representation, extracts of important letters, etc. Significant documents transmitted by Thomson include the following: a letter regarding disorder in Massachusetts (1786 Dec. 14); a resolution for a Convention of delegates to meet in May 1787 to revise the Articles of Confederation (1787 Feb. 21); resolutions regarding a treaty of peace with Great Britain (1787 April 13); resolutions empowering the Board of Treasury to contract for coining copper, the sale of lands surveyed in the Western Territory, & the extension of the ''franking'' privilege to members of the Constitutional Convention (1787 April 25); a treaty between the U.S. and the Kingdom of Morocco (1787 July 21); a letter informing the Governor of the election of Cyrus Griffin as President of the Continental Congress (1788 Jan. 23); a resolution on the claims of David Henley, Commissioner for the Claims of Virginia on Account of the Western Territory (1788 June 4); and a letter regarding the proceedings of Congress on the independence of the District of Kentucky (1788 July 3).
John Jay, as Secretary of Foreign Affairs, communicates to Governor Randolph issues abroad. He encloses an extract of a letter he received from John Adams, Minister Plenipotentiary of the U.S. in London, regarding the counterfeiting of Carolina money (1787 July 3). Jay also encloses a copy of the signals agreed upon between the U.S. & Morocco for their vessels at sea (1787 July 27). On 26 May 1788, Jay drafted a letter to the Governor regarding a note from Schultz von Asheraden, Envoy Extraordinary of the King of Sweden, in reference to Capt. Adolph Frederick Dahlberg. Similarly, there is also a letter from Jay regarding notes from the Minister of France on the conduct of J.M. Ferrier (1788 June 13). Lastly, there is a letter respecting foreign consuls (1788 Sept. 24).
Henry Knox, Secretary of War, corresponds with the Governor on 12 February 1787 on the subject of the Board of Treasury's plan to provide for the establishment of troops and the insurrection in Massachusetts. There is also a letter from Knox concerning the appointment of Joseph Martin as Indian Agent for the Cherokee Nation (1788 June 23).
Joseph Martin, Agent for Indian Affairs and later Indian Agent for the Cherokee Nation, corresponds with Governor Randolph on many occasions. Martin writes the Governor on 16 March 1787 concerning the opening of the land office of the state of Franklin and Benjamin Logan's attack on Crow Town. On March 21, Martin's letter mentions the Chota Indians and the taking of land by the ''Franklynists.'' His letter of June 28 encloses Indian talks from Cherokee chiefs including King Fisher, Old Corn Tassle, & Tuskegetchee. He writes about the dispute between North Carolina and the state of Franklin in April 1788 and encloses a letter from John Sevier & the Cherokees. Finally, he informs the Governor of attacks against the Cherokee nation and encloses letters from Andrew McGilveray regarding Indian affairs (1788 June 11).
Samuel Osgood, Walter Livingston, & Arthur Lee of the U.S. Board of Treasury transmit a statement of the contingent expenditures of the U.S. from 1 January to 31 December 1786 (1787 Feb. 2). They also enclose an act of Congress regarding the repeal of another act to open a loan on the credit of the requisition (1787 May 15). On May 25, the Board writes the Governor concerning an ordinance of Congress for the settlement of accounts between individual states and the U.S. Finally, the Board encloses a letter & report to the state of Connecticut regarding invalid pensions (1788 Sept. 19).
The various members of Virginia's delegation to Congress regularly communicated with Governor Randolph on a variety of national concerns. The delegation to the Continental Congress during Randolph's administration consisted of Edward Carrington, William Grayson, James Madison, Richard H. Lee, Cyrus Griffin, Henry Lee, & John Brown. Significant correspondence from these delegates relate to Shay's Rebellion in Massachusetts (1786 December 8); the need for military stores in the Western Country (1786 December 24); Gen. Knox and arms for the state of Virginia (1787 Feb. 19); the treaty between the U.S. and United Netherlands (1787 March 5); the progress of the appointments to the Convention and the admission of Vermont to the Union (1787 March 19); trade laws, an act to ratify & confirm the independence of Vermont, the appointment of John Pierce as Commissioner for Settlement of the Illinois Accounts, the discharge of troops under the act of October 1786, the death of Vergennes, & hostilities in the Western Country (1787 April 2, 12, 13, & July 17); the inadequacy of the government due to the irregular representation in Congress, commercial deputies, & indents for 1786 & 1787 (1787 May 7, 15, & June 8); communications from Col. Evan Shelby, the dismemberment of states, Vermont, North Carolina, & problems in the Kaskaskies & Post Vincent (1787 June 12); the defense of the frontiers of Kentucky and elsewhere (1787 June 25, 27, & July 7); the Board of Treasury (1787 July 1787); an ordinance for establishing a temporary government in the Western Territory, a resolution concerning copper coinage, & an ordinance for settling the accounts between the U.S. and individual states (1787 Nov. 3); the claim of Virginia to the Northwestern Territory (1788 March 23); the settlement of the accounts of the state against the U.S. (1788 May 8); an act to extend the time to settle these accounts (1788 June 9); and rations for rangers called into service in Bourbon County (1788 June 30).
The various members of Virginia's delegation to Congress regularly communicated with Governor Randolph on a variety of national concerns. The delegation to the Continental Congress during Randolph's administration consisted of Edward Carrington, William Grayson, James Madison, Richard H. Lee, Cyrus Griffin, Henry Lee, & John Brown. Significant correspondence from these delegates relate to Shay's Rebellion in Massachusetts (1786 December 8); the need for military stores in the Western Country (1786 December 24); Gen. Knox and arms for the state of Virginia (1787 Feb. 19); the treaty between the U.S. and United Netherlands (1787 March 5); the progress of the appointments to the Convention and the admission of Vermont to the Union (1787 March 19); trade laws, an act to ratify & confirm the independence of Vermont, the appointment of John Pierce as Commissioner for Settlement of the Illinois Accounts, the discharge of troops under the act of October 1786, the death of Vergennes, & hostilities in the Western Country (1787 April 2, 12, 13, & July 17); the inadequacy of the government due to the irregular representation in Congress, commercial deputies, & indents for 1786 & 1787 (1787 May 7, 15, & June 8); communications from Col. Evan Shelby, the dismemberment of states, Vermont, North Carolina, & problems in the Kaskaskies & Post Vincent (1787 June 12); the defense of the frontiers of Kentucky and elsewhere (1787 June 25, 27, & July 7); the Board of Treasury (1787 July 1787); an ordinance for establishing a temporary government in the Western Territory, a resolution concerning copper coinage, & an ordinance for settling the accounts between the U.S. and individual states (1787 Nov. 3); the claim of Virginia to the Northwestern Territory (1788 March 23); the settlement of the accounts of the state against the U.S. (1788 May 8); an act to extend the time to settle these accounts (1788 June 9); and rations for rangers called into service in Bourbon County (1788 June 30).
Significant correspondents from Virginia State government include John Beckley, Clerk of the House of Delegates, Humphrey Brooke, Clerk of the Senate; Archibald Blair, Clerk of the Council of State; Capt. John Peyton & Capt. Elias Langham, Superintendent of the Military Stores, Arms, & Ammunition at Point of Fork Arsenal; Col. Thomas Meriwether, Commissioner of Army Accounts; Benjamin Logan, County Lieutenant of Lincoln County; Arthur Campbell, County Lieutenant of Washington County; Levi Todd, County Lieutenant of Fayette County; Alexander Barnett, County Lieutenant of Russell County; David Shepherd, County Lieutenant of Ohio County; Walter Crockett, County Lieutenant of Montgomery County; William Rose, Keeper of the Public Jail; James Innes, Attorney General; Leighton Wood, Jr., Solicitor General; Andrew Dunscomb, Assistant Commissioner of Military Claims; Capt. James Barron & Capt. Richard Taylor, Virginia Navy; Beverley Randolph, Lieutenant Governor; and Jacquelin Ambler, Treasurer.
John Beckley, Clerk of the House of Delegates, & Humphrey Brooke, Clerk of the Senate, regularly enclose resolutions from their respective bodies to the Governor. On 1 December 1786, Beckley submits the appointment of Henry Lee as Delegate to Congress. He provides resolutions regarding the claims of the state of Virginia against the United States and the election of Andrew Dunscomb to serve as Commissioner to settle these accounts (1787 Jan. 5). On 23 October 1787, Beckley transmits an extract of the journal of the House of Delegates containing the ballot for five delegates in Congress including James Madison, Edward Carrington, Henry Lee, John Brown, & Cyrus Griffin. On 31 October 1788, he presents the ballot for the election of Cyrus Griffin, John Brown, James Madison, Jr., John Dawson, & Mann Page. In addition, an extract of the journal of the House of Delegates from 8 November 1788 reports on the election of Richard Henry Lee & William Grayson as Virginia's first senators in Congress. Beckley & Brooke also inform the Governor about appointments to the Privy Council including William Heth & Joseph Eggleston (1787 November 7) and Andrew Moore & Robert Goode (1788 June 28). Lastly, the clerks inform the Governor of the election of Edmund Winston as judge of the General Court (1788 June 28).
Archibald Blair, as Clerk of the Council of State, encloses orders of the Council to the Governor. In December 1786, the Council orders Col. Meriwether to contract for repairs to the Public Jail & the Governor's House, to employ someone to convey arms from France, & to purchase a sword for Capt. Jouett (1786 Dec. 14). Meriwether also receives orders related to the distribution of Articles of War (1787 May 2). His letter dated 2 May 1787 also relates to alterations in the Public Jail. The Council sends a list of grants to be signed by the Governor (1787 April 30 & 25 May). Lastly, the Council provides advice on the requisition of militia in the western counties including a resolution of Congress concerning orders for militia in Virginia & Pennsylvania to be ready to protect the inhabitants (1788 Oct. 15).
Capt. John Peyton resigns as Commissary of Stores at Point of Fork on 20 November 1786. Peyton writes to Col. Thomas Meriwether on 10 December 1786 recommending William Price, his former clerk, to succeed him. Additionally, there are letters from other individuals applying for the position. Elias Langham, however, successfully applies to the Governor on 13 December 1786. As Commissary of Military Stores, Langham corresponds with Col. Meriwether regarding provisions (1786 Dec. 25); contracts to supply rations (1787 April 26); an estimate of clothing for guards and state negroes (1787 July 5); & land belonging to David Ross near Point of Fork in Fluvanna County (1787 June 26 & Dec. 21). In turn, Col. Meriwether corresponds with Governor Randolph offering an estimate of the cost of transporting arms from Point of Fork to Redstone (1786 Dec. 26), a report of Capt. Peyton's last returns (1787 Feb. 22), delinquencies of militia officers (1787 March 1), payrolls of Point of Fork (1787 April 7), a list of his official duties (1787 May 8), a report of the militia (1787 Oct. 22), and reports on the Point of Fork Arsenal (1787 Oct. 4 & 1788 Oct. 3).
County lieutenants including Levi Todd, Benjamin Logan, Arthur Campbell, David Shepherd, Alexander Barnett, & Walter Crockett from the western counties correspond with Governor Randolph on numerous occasions primarily regarding Indian affairs. Levi Todd writes about the strength of the militia in Fayette County and Shawnee attacks in the area (1786 Dec. 7); the need for officers & a lack of ammunition and provision (1787 Feb. 14); the defenselessness of Kentucky (1787 April 30); & war with the Indians (1788 March 29). Benjamin Logan writes about an attack on the Shawnee towns in the District of Kentucky (1786 Dec. 17); Indian outrages in Kentucky (1787 April 14); the sense of the people of Kentucky regarding the Cherokee Indians (1787 May 17); intelligence concerning the Cherokee Indians sent to Arthur Campbell (1787 May 18); & the proceedings of a meeting of the commanding officers of the District of Kentucky (1787 Sept. 24). Arthur Campbell communicates a list of field officers & captains proposed to command two regiments of militia in Washington County (1787 Feb. 14); the implications of the recent treaty with Spain (1787 Feb. 16); an attack by Col. John Logan on friendly Indians (1787 March 9); the militia in Washington County and the apprehended danger from the Cherokee Indians (1787 March 17); westward expansion, Topoka, Chief of the Chocta Nation, & the navigation of the Mississippi (1787 April 15); movements of the Cherokee Indians (1787 Aug. 16); the boundary between Virginia & North Carolina (1787 Dec. 10); & consideration for the position as Superintendent of the Southern Department (1787 Dec. 31). David Shepherd expresses his concerns in relation to Indian outrages in Monongalia (1787 April 30); Indian attacks & the state of the militia in Ohio County (1787 May 24 & 1787 Nov. 10). Finally, Alexander Barnett writes on Indian attacks in Russell County (1787 May 19 & 1787 Aug. 29) & Walter Crockett relates incidents with natives in Montgomery County (1787 June 11 & 1788 March 15).
William Rose as Keeper of the Public Jail periodically transmits lists or calendars of criminals convicted at the General Court (1786 Dec. 16, 1787 March 28, 1787 April 30, 1787 June 11, 1787 Dec. 6, 1788 March 31, 1788 April 26, 1788 June 10, 1788 Oct. 27). Rose also writes to the Governor regarding specific criminals in his jail (1787 Jan. 24 & 1787 July 26). Lastly, he send his remarks on a contract to furnish the Public Jail with provisions (1788 Jan. 30).
James Innes served as Attorney General to the Commonwealth during Randolph's administration as Governor. Innes provides his opinion on various issues including the repeal of the act of 1785 for approving, confirming, & ratifying the compact between Virginia & Maryland (1787 Feb. 28 & 1787 Aug. 3); tobacco inspection at Lynch's Ferry (1787 June 26 & 1787 Sept. 1); & foreign creditors (1787 March 19).
Andrew Dunscomb's correspondence relates to his position as Assistant Commissioner of Military Claims. Included is his oath of office and a letter regarding the same (1787 Jan. 13 & 15). He also writes on the state of claims of the Commonwealth with the U.S. (1787 June 13, 18, & Nov. 15). On 6 July 1787, he requests additional clerks, and later, he asks the Governor for a salary increase (1787 Nov. 13). Similarly, there is extensive correspondence from Leighton Wood, Jr., Solicitor General, regarding claims against the state, delinquencies of sheriffs in paying taxes, etc. Present is Wood's bond & security for his position as Solicitor (1787 Jan. 26 & Feb. 1). Treasurer, Jacquelin Ambler's letters too relate to the financial matters of the state. Ambler reveals a lack of money in the Contingent Fund for William Rose's warrants for the support of the Public Jail (1787 March 5).
Capt. James Barron, Virginia State Navy, died in May 1787. Applications can be found to replace him as commander of the state boats (1787 June 4). Before his death, Barron comments on the transport of small arms from Norfolk (1786 Dec. 6) and discusses the employment of a surgeon & pilots on his boats (1787 April 27). Barron was replaced by Capt. Richard Taylor in June 1787. Noteworthy among his correspondence, Taylor encloses an inventory of the articles on board the Liberty and Patriot on 12 August 1787. He also remarks on the poor state of the boats in his letter dated 7 September 1787. On 14 November 1787, Taylor complains to the Governor about his pay & pension. Lastly, Taylor talks about damage sustained to the Schooner Patriot in a storm while harbored at Portsmouth (1788 July 24).